A Guide to the Virginia Fire and Police Museum Collection, 1879-1985
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Virginia Fire and Police Museum Collection, 1879-1985
Library of Virginia
37327
33 microfilm reels.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Lent for microfilming by the Virginia Fire and Police Museum, 23 November 1999.
Biographical/Historical Information
The Virginia Fire and Museum was founded in 1976 and is located in the oldest standing firehouse in Richmond, Virginia. The building, which served as the home for Steamer Company number 5 from 1849 to 1968 and for the 3rd police station from 1865 to 1898, was slated for demolition in 1976. However, the building was saved to serve as the home for the museum. The museum offers visitors a lesson in police and firefighting architecture, uniforms, and equipment, and provides an educational program on fire and life safety.
Scope and Content Information
Collection, 1879-1985, of the Virginia Fire and Police Museum consisting of log books, supply books and lists, miscellaneous records, insurance brochures, reports on personnel and equipment, accounts and account books, requisitions, inventories, correspondence, house fund books, directories, lists of personnel, personnel histories, leave log books, Fireman's Mutual Aid Society records, burial funds, Fort Lee Fire Department time and attendance books, Board of Fire Commissioners meeting minutes, records of fires in Richmond, visitors register to the Virginia Fire and Police Museum, and miscellaneous loose papers. Log books contain company rosters, duties, watches, daily and monthly reports, alarms, equipment checks, leaves, absences, addresses and telephone numbers, supplies, accounts, weather observations, and other information. Loose papers consist of advertisements, calendars, department orders, receipts, vehicle reports, and other miscellaneous items.
Contents List
- Truck Co. No. 1 Log Book, 1 July 1903-1917 (target incorrect) (Reel 2208)
- Truck Co. No. 1 Log Book, 30 September 1916-8 April 1928 (loose papers, 1916-1935) (Reel 2208)
- Truck Co. No. 1 Log Book, 23 November 1916-16 September 1917 (Reel 2208)
- Truck Co. No. 1 Log Book, 1 February 1916-22 November 1916 (Reel 2208)
- Truck Co. No. 1 Log Book, 17 September 1917-30 March 1918 (Reel 2208)
- Truck Co. No. 1 Supplies, January 1939-October 1941 (loose papers) (Reel 2209)
- Engine Co. No. 3 Log Book, 1 July 1903-1914 (target incorrect) (Reel 2209)
- Engine Co. No. 3 Log Book, 1 February 1916-24 November 1916 (Reel 2209)
- Engine Co. No. 3 Log Book, 14 October 1916-31 December 1924 (Reel 2209)
- Engine Co. No. 3 Log Book, 2 September 1917-21 March 1918 (Reel 2209)
- Engine Co. No. 3 Log Book and Supplies, 1925-1933 (Reel 2209)
- Engine Co. No. 3 and Truck Co. No. 1 Log Book, 1 July 1931-21 April 1932 (Reel 2210)
- Engine Co. No. 3 Log Book, 1 January 1925-1 September 1931 (Reel 2210)
- Engine Co. No. 3 and Truck Co. No. 2 Log Book, 16 October 1938-9 August 1939 (Reel 2210)
- Engine Co. No. 4 Log Book, 1 August 1902-23 August 1905 (Reel 2210)
- Engine Co. No. 4 Log Book, 1 July 1903-31 March 1907 (Reel 2210)
- Engine Co. No. 4 Log Book, 1 April 1907-31 December 1910 (Reel 2211)
- Engine Co. No. 4 Log Book, 1 January 1911-31 March 1912 (Reel 2211)
- Engine Co. No. 4(?) Supplies, 27 July 1911-December 1914 (target incorrect) (Reel 2211)
- Engine Co. No. 4(?) Log Book, 1 July 1915-26 November 1916, and miscellaneous records, 1903-1937 (Reel 2211)
- Engine Co. No. 4 Log Book, 1 February 1916-14 October 1916 (Reel 2211)
- Engine Co. No. 4 Log Book, 14 October 1916-3 July 1917 (Reel 2211)
- Engine Co. No. 4 Log Book, 26 January 1919-17 February 1920 (Reel 2212)
- Engine Co. No. 4 Log Book, 7 May 1919-13 May 1921 (Reel 2212)
- Engine Co. No. 4 Log Book, 1 July 1915-25 November 1916 (target incorrect) (Reel 2212)
- Engine Co. No. 4 Log Book, 1 January 1922-31 January 1926 (Reel 2212)
- Engine Co. No. 4 Log Book, 1 February 1926-31 August 1927 (Reel 2213)
- Engine Co. No. 4(?) Log Book and miscellaneous records, 1920-1955 (target incorrect) (Reel 2213)
- Engine Co. No. 4 Log Book, 1 March 1927-1 March 1929 (Reel 2213)
- Engine Co. No. 4 Log Book, 1 March 1929-31 December 1930 (Reel 2213)
- Engine Co. No. 4 Log Book, 1 January 1933-31 July 1935 (Reel 2214)
- Engine Co. No. 4 (?) Log Book, 31 July 1935-30 June 1939 (Reel 2214)
- Engine Co. No. 4 Log Book, 1 July 1939-30 April 1940 (Reel 2214)
- Engine Co. No. 4 Log Book, 1 January 1941-31 December 1942 (Reel 2214)
- Engine Co. No. 4 Log Book, 1 January 1937-1946 (Reel 2215)
- Engine Co. No. 4 Log Book, 1943-1949 (target incorrect) (Reel 2215)
- Engine Co. No. 5 Log Book, 2 September 1906-14 December 1912 (Reel 2215)
- Various Reports on Facilities, Personnel, and Equipment, 1912-1934 (target incorrect) (Reel 2215)
- Engine Co. No. 5 Log Book, 1 July 1909-30 December 1914, (loose papers, 1911-1912, 1941) (Reel 2215)
- Engine Co. No. 5(?) Supplies, 1 January 1913-3 April 1918 (Reel 2215)
- Engine Co. No. 5 Log Book, 16 July 1916-25 November 1916 (Reel 2215)
- Engine Co. No. 5(?) Log Book, 1 January 1916-18 September 1917 (Reel 2216)
- Engine Co. No. 5(?) Log Book, 21 April 1920-22 May 1921 (Reel 2216)
- Engine Co. No. 5 and Truck Co. No. 1 Log Book, 1 January 1925-24 October 1925 (Reel 2216)
- Engine Co. No. 5 Log Book, 20 May 1924-13 March 1925 (loose papers, 1924-1925) (Reel 2216)
- Engine Co. No. 5 Log Book, 21 July 1923-19 May 1924 (loose papers, 1924-1925) (Reel 2217)
- Engine Co. No. 5 Log Book, 1926 (Reel 2217)
- Steamer Co. No. 5 Log Book, 1926 (Reel 2217)
- Engine Co. No. 5 Log Book, 24 October 1926-27 August 1927 (Reel 2217)
- Engine Co. No. 5 Log Book, 1 January 1926-31 December 1931 (miscellaneous records, 1903-1933) (Reel 2218)
- Engine Co. No. 5 Log Book, 23 June 1928-13 April 1929 (Reel 2218)
- Engine Co. No. 5 Log Book, 14 April 1929-7 February 1930 (Reel 2218)
- Engine Co. No. 5 Log Book, 21 May 1933-15 March 1934 (Reel 2218)
- Engine Co. No. 7 Log Book, 1 January 1935-30 May 1938 (Reel 2219)
- Engine Co. No. 5 Various Reports on Facilities, Personnel, and Equipment, 1934-1937 (Reel 2219)
- Engine Co. No. 5 Log Book, 1 September 1931-30 April 1939 (Reel 2219)
- Engine Co. No. 5 Log Book, 1 September 1943-31 December 1944 (Reel 2219)
- Steamer Co. No. 5 Requisitions, 21 April 1890-3 May 1901 (Reel 2219)
- Engine Co. No. 5 Log of Vehicle Repairs, etc., 1960-1970 (loose papers, 1964) (Reel 2220)
- Engine Co. No. 6 Log Book, 1 February 1916-19 November 1916 (Reel 2220)
- Engine Co. No. 6 Log Book, 6 May 1919-8 June 1920 (Reel 2220)
- Engine Co. No. 6 Log Book, 1 November 1925-15 August 1926 (Reel 2220)
- Engine Co. No. 6 Log Book, 1 January 1931-31 December 1932 (Reel 2221)
- Engine Co. No. 6 Log Book, 1 January 1944-31 December 1944 (loose papers, 1941-1943) (Reel 2221)
- Engine Co. No. 7 Log Book, 1 April 1913-23 April 1921 (Reel 2221)
- Engine Co. No. 7 Log Book and miscellaneous information, 4 October 1909-1 April 1913 (Reel 2221)
- Engine Co. No. 7 Log Book, 19 June 1917-5 January 1918 (Reel 2222)
- Engine Co. No. 7 Log Book, 20 July 1918-5 February 1919 (Reel 2222)
- Engine Co. No. 7 Log Book, 10 May 1932-28 February 1933 (Reel 2222)
- Engine Co. No. 7(?) Supplies, 1919-1936 (Reel 2222)
- Engine Co. No. 7 Log Book, 7 January 1925-1 November 1925 (Reel 2222)
- Engine Co. No. 7 Log Book, 24 August 1926-10 June 1927 (Reel 2223)
- Engine Co. No. 7 Log Book, 5 April 1928-30 January 1929 (Reel 2223)
- Engine Co. No. 7 Log Book, 30 January 1929-26 November 1929 (Reel 2223)
- Engine Co. No. 7 Log Book, 22 September 1930-19 July 1931 (Reel 2223)
- Engine Co. No. 7 Automatic Sprinkler Cut-off Log and Personnel Information, 1928-1936 (Reel 2224)
- Engine Co. No. 7 Log Book, 10 June 1927-3 April 1928 (Reel 2224)
- Engine Co. No. 7 Log Book, 26 November 1929-21 July 1930 (Reel 2224)
- Engine Co. No. 7 Log Book, 25 December 1933-21 October 1934 (Reel 2224)
- Engine Co. No. 7 Log Book, 2 November 1935-1 December 1936 (Reel 2224)
- Engine Co. No. 7 Log Book, 1 August 1942-23 May 1943 (Reel 2225)
- Truck Co. No. 7(?) Inventories and Address Reports, 1937-1945 (Reel 2225)
- Engine Co. No. 7 Log Book, 20 August 1939-10 June 1940 (Reel 2225)
- Engine Co. No. 7 Log Book, 23 May 1943-14 March 1944 (Reel 2225)
- Engine Co. No. 7 Log Book, 16 November 1908-1 February 1916 (loose papers) (Reel 2225)
- Engine Co. No. 3 Log Book, 22 March 1918-29 September 1918 (Reel 2226)
- Engine Co. No. 12 Log Book, 2 April 1918-22 October 1918 (Reel 2226)
- Engine Co. No. 12 Log Book, 23 October 1918-6 May 1919 (Reel 2226)
- Engine Co. No. 12 Log Book, 1 February 1916-26 November 1916 (Reel 2226)
- Engine Co. No. 12 Log Book, 19 September 1917-31 March 1918 (Reel 2226)
- Engine Co. No. 12 Log Book, 3 November 1923-21 March 1925 (Reel 2226)
- Engine Co. No. 12 Log Book, 17 August 1943-28 April 1945 (Reel 2227)
- Engine Co. No. 13(?) Log Book and miscellaneous records, 1922-1935 (target incorrect) (Reel 2227)
- Engine Co. No. 15 Log Book, 1 January 1937-30 June 1938 (Reel 2227)
- Engine Co. No. 15 Log Book, 1 April 1933-31 August 1934 (loose papers, 1936-1937) (Reel 2227)
- Engine Co. No. 15 Log Book, 14 March 1944-6 January 1945 (Reel 2228)
- Hook and Ladder Truck Co. No. 2 Log Book, 1 April 1883-28 December 1900 (Reel 2228)
- Engine Co. No. 4(?) Requisitions and Supplies, 1900-1910 (Reel 2228)
- Richmond Fire Department, Unidentified Firehouse Account Book, 1901-1904 (undated loose papers) (Reel 2228)
- Richmond Fire Department, Unidentified Firehouse Log Book, 12 May 1907-31 December 1907 (Reel 2228)
- Richmond Fire Department Unidentified Firehouse Log Book, 11 May 1911-22 November 1915 (Reel 2229)
- Richmond Fire Department Unidentified Firehouse Account Book, 1915-1930 (Reel 2229)
- Richmond Fire Department Unidentified Firehouse Log Book, 1 January 1914-1 July 1915 (Reel 2229)
- Richmond Fire Department Unidentified Firehouse Log Book, 26 November 1916-5 March 1918 (Reel 2229)
- Richmond Fire Department Unidentified Firehouse Log Book, 4 July 1917-21 December 1918 (Reel 2229)
- Richmond Fire Department Unidentified Firehouse Log Book, 3 April 1918-10 August 1918 (entries, November 1931) (Reel 2230)
- Richmond Fire Department Unidentified Firehouse Log Book, 18 June 1918-25 January 1919 (Reel 2230)
- Richmond Fire Department Unidentified Firehouse Log Book, 20 April 1919-20 May 1920 (Reel 2230)
- Richmond Fire Department Unidentified Firehouse Log Book, 18 February 1920-2 January 1921 (Reel 2230)
- Richmond Fire Department Unidentified Firehouse Log Book, 2 January 1921-25 November 1921 (Reel 2231)
- Richmond Fire Department Unidentified Firehouse Personnel and Apparatus Records, 1929-1945 (Reel 2231)
- Richmond Fire Department Unidentified Firehouse Log Book, 19 July 1931-10 May 1932 (silent alarms, 1944-1945) (Reel 2232)
- Richmond Fire Department Unidentified Firehouse Log Book, 16 May 1930-17 November 1935 (Reel 2232)
- Richmond Fire Department Unidentified Firehouse Log Book, 1 May 1940-31 December 1940 (Reel 2232)
- Richmond Fire Department Unidentified Firehouse Log Book, 12 September 1940-17 December 1940 (Reel 2232)
- Richmond Fire Department Unidentified Firehouse Log Book, 10 October 1941-31 July 1942 (Reel 2232)
- Richmond Fire Department Unidentified Firehouse Log Book and List of Alarm Calls, 1 September 1944-17 December 1955 (Reel 2233)
- Richmond Fire Department Unidentified Firehouse House Fund, 1921-1924 (Reel 2233)
- Richmond Fire Department Unidentified Firehouse Log Book, 3 September 1918-20 March 1919 (target incorrect) (Reel 2233)
- Directory of Personnel, 1907-1912 (Reel 2233)
- Richmond Fire Department List of Personnel, 1 July 1912-1 July 1915 (Reel 2233)
- Richmond Fire Department Personnel Histories (loose pages: index), 1915-1918 (Reel 2234)
- Richmond Fire Department Personnel Histories, 1919-1926 (Reel 2234)
- Sick, Injured, Furlough and Special Leave Log Book, 1921 (Reel 2234)
- Sick, Injured, Furlough and Special Leave Log Book, 1922 (Reel 2234)
- Sick, Injured, Furlough and Special Leave Log Book, 1923 (Reel 2234)
- Sick and Injured Lists, 1924 (Reel 2234)
- Sick, Injured, Furlough and Special Leave Log Book, 1925 (Reel 2234)
- Sick, Injured, Furlough and Special Leave Log Book, 1926 (Reel 2234)
- Fireman's Mutual Aid Society, Richmond Roll of Contributing Members, loose papers, 1921-1923 (Reel 2234)
- Richmond Fire Department Burial Fund, 1935-1958 (Reel 2234)
- Fort Lee Fire Department Time and Attendance, July 1945-February 1953 (September 1957) (Reel 2235)
- Motor Apparatus Installed and Transferred Since January 1919, Log Book, 1919-1932 (loose papers, 1915-1927) (Reel 2235)
- Alarms Received, 1 July 1900-31 December 1908 (Reel 2235)
- Alarm Box Log and Regular Log Book, 1938-1945 (Reel 2235)
- Fire Department Burial Fund, 1942-1946 (Reel 2235)
- Apparatus Inspections, 1942-1946 (Reel 2235)
- Supplies Ordered, 1941-1954 (Reel 2235)
- Supplies Ordered and Log Book, 1947-1953 (Reel 2235)
- Account Ledger, 1926-1929 (Reel 2235)
- Supplies Ordered Log Book, 1926-1929 (Reel 2236)
- Virginia Fire and Police Museum Steamer Co. No. 5 Visitors Log, 7 October 1978-18 May 1985 (Reel 2236)
- Board of Fire Commissioners, Minutes of Meetings, 2 July 1888-31 December 1894 (Reel 2236)
- Index to Proceedings of the Board of Fire Commissioners of Richmond, Virginia, Commencing January 8 1894 Ending December 31 1894 (Reel 2236)
- Board of Fire Commissioners, Minutes of Meetings, 14 January 1895-24 June 1907 (Reel 2237)
- Board of Commissioners, Index to Minutes of Meetings (Reel 2237)
- Board of Fire Commissioners, Minutes of Meetings, 10 November 1913-17 November 1918 (Reel 2237)
- Richmond Fire Department Records of Fires, 24 January 1879-29 December 1896 (Reel 2238)
- Richmond Fire Department Official Records of Fires, 1 January 1897-1 January 1916 (Reel 2238)
- Richmond Fire Department Record of Fires, 1 January 1916-27 December 1924 (loose papers, 1921) (Reel 2239)
- Richmond Fire Department Record of Fires, 1 January 1925-31 December 1931 (loose papers, 1931-1940) (Reel 2239)
- Directory of Personnel Listed by Companies, 1903-1913 (Reel 2240)